so thanks so much for that participation
I hope you met a couple of more people
that you hadn't seen before
and slightly awkward in this face
because I really can't see you I'm kind
of looking into the light but which
might be a good thing so my presentation
is a pretty heavy title holes dynamic
hole systems design how can we weave
ecosystems of collaboration and as you
can imagine I could easily talk about
this for a couple of hours or a couple
of days so I'm just gonna give you some
snippets some a feeling for what I mean
by this we all know that we live in an
extremely complex ending world that
we're facing a complexity that we might
not be fully prepared for yet and
mathematically speaking in the world of
complexity when you look into what that
actually is it's any system with more
than three interacting variables is a
complex dynamic system and these systems
are fundamentally unpredictable and
uncontrollable so we have to learn to
dance with this complexity and stop
trying to control things this slide is
from a colleague of mine from the
international futures forum and it's
from 2002 and if you can read it's a bit
of a small screen but if you can read
what's on these little arrows these
issues existed in 2002 and they even
more pressing now I'm going to try to
keep the bad news as short as possible
but I think it's summarized in those
four slides or those four images and
business as usual is not no longer an
option the one in the top left corner
comes from a paper from the Stockholm
resilience center that was published in
August and it's called something climate
change in the Anthropocene and basically
it says that we are at a point where
we've destabilized the global climate
system to a degree that we're now in the
beginning of what's called runaway
climate
where certain triggers in the climate
system actually amplify the change and
where the possibility to move back will
soon not be an option anymore so we
really Antonio Guterres the
secretary-general of the United Nations
has recently said that we've got a year
and a half as a global community to
respond seriously to climate change them
otherwise it might be too late
and then the graphic below that with all
these rising exponential curves they're
basically all about water use energy use
and the amount of McDonald's restaurants
in the world like basically everything
is going up and if we don't make it on
the tombstone of humanity the words will
be this species didn't understand
exponential growth we just assumed that
things will go on more or less like we
accustomed to but we're now in that
steep end of the exponential curve and
things will change then the top right
corner is que Dre Werth's
donut which is trying to put two things
together it's on the one hand the
planetary boundaries issues like climate
change ocean acidification all the the
key parameters of the planetary
life-support system that we've already
overstepped and what's inside the circle
the red reaching into the circle is
where we don't meet the social
foundations of building a healthy and
viable society so it's not just about
environmental issues it's all social
issues as well and that pyramid at the
bottom is from a report that credit
Swiss gives out every two years it's
called the Global Wealth Report and
basically we now live in a world where
eight point six percent of humanity hold
85% of the global wealth eight point six
percent of humanity owned eighty five
point six percent of the global wealth
but what's even most staggering is that
71 percent of humanity have to share
three percent of the
so again business as usual is no longer
an option we cannot sustain the world
that is that unequal and would we want
to sustain the world that is that
unequal so when I asked you about
are you keeping business as usual or are
you keeping the lights on are you a
visionary
are you an entrepreneur tweaking what is
possible this is to give you an embodied
feeling of where you feel most aligned
with this particular framework that
again friends of mine in the
international futures forum have
developed it's called the three horizons
framework and I encourage you whatever
you do to look this up because if you
want to implement something in the long
term and you need the voices of the
practical day-to-day you need the voices
of the visionary in the room and you
need the voices of what can we do
tomorrow what is feasible already then
this is a wonderful map that where a
bunch of post-its collecting ideas and
working with it you can you can actually
step into that space you could say that
the red curve is business as usual the
world in crisis the green curve is a
viable future tomorrow's land if we make
it and the blue curve is the
entrepreneur building the bridge between
the term but most importantly it's a way
to value all these voices and all these
perspectives on the future because if we
want to build a future that works for we
need to include everybody and the time
of them against us is over
we're on living spaceship earth the ship
is sinking it's taking on water either
we do it together or there might not be
a 22nd century with a lot of happy
humans around him and the exercise that
we did last with the cards is to
introduce you to the sustainable
development goals it's an imperfect
platform like most
platforms that have been created like
this particular one by the United
Nations has has come out of the largest
consulted Tory process that the United
Nations have ever engaged in over a
million people from all the countries
around the world have somehow
contributed to this a group of over
3,000 scientists and and selected people
have been working diligently on trying
to make these goals the best they could
they are some critiques in the activist
movement that for example goal number 8
which still names economic growth as a
goal rather than as part of a
dysfunctional economic system that we
need to fundamentally transform and
sabotages all the other ones yes that
might be true so we need to reframe that
economic growth to may be qualitative
growth but rather than dismissing the
SDGs altogether I would invite you to
understand them as a platform of
conversation that for the first time is
bringing supranational and national
support to a local level so you can
actually have the conversation around
how are these goals relevant to us here
in Merseyside or wherever you come from
and how can we somewhat counter co-opt
them using the fact that they're now in
national plans and there is
international funding to it for
implementation to make them meaningful
to us and I work part time for an
organization called Gaia education and I
actually designed the cards that you
were just using and basically that's
what they're what they are they're our
facilitation tool where you can start
conversations with people in your
community around how to implement the
SDGs in ways that are meaningful to your
community and it comes together with a
manual which is called the multipliers
manual we run a one-day or a half like
there's two versions a half-day and a
full-day training called the training of
multipliers
and the manual details minute-by-minute
a kind of facilitator script on how to
run this workshop so you can choose
whether you want to first do one that
guy education offer somewhere in the
world you can bring them here and and
and have them run one but if you just
want to run with it yourself you just
download the black and white version of
them the multipliers handbook and if you
have any basic skills as a group
facilitator and organizer you'll see
that it's it's very self-explanatory so
all you need is a set of these cards and
you're off and basically the different
steps will show you first then make
people familiar with the stds then they
look at mapping what's already happening
in my community that might not be framed
under an SDG but if if i do a local
water project on cleaning up polluted
waters or giving people access to better
drinking water then that's already a
project working on an SD g and then you
identify the the low-hanging fruits in
your community where you can do big
changes and then you identify where
there's missing gaps and in in the
bottom left corner is some of you might
be familiar with the business model
canvas this is this is a kind of SDG
version of the business model canvas
it's another step in a facilitation
process where once people have
identified a project that ideally
addresses three or four of the SDGs
together because they have to be
addressed together and then this step in
the workshop helps you to deepen in into
that and in general guide ucation does a
lot of capacity-building all around the
world we have partners over a hundred
partners in 52 countries around the
world on all the continents ba
Antarctica and we haven't face-to-face
125 our course which is was initially
called eco village design education but
it's really about building sustainable
communities so it's also very relevant
for people in a transition town movement
or who just wanted to neighborhood work
then there's a 400 hour online course
called design for sustainability and if
you just at that point in in your work
where you feel actually everything has
to be sustainable because no matter what
our future will bring if if we don't
make it sustainable or regenerative then
it will not last into the distant future
but you feel you still need to brush up
on a whole system's perspective of what
that actually means that causes is a
great opportunity to do so and and then
we also run lots of project-based
learning works in Bangladesh in Senegal
in favelas in Brazil where people apply
there's kind of whole system's thinking
of sustainability and the phrase that
I've got there at the bottom is it's
really when you work in a systemic way
then you stop thinking that's my problem
how do I solve it the first question is
give me at least five or six more
problems and then you look at what kind
of project can I build that would solve
all of them at once because it's the
siloed thinking even in trying to create
solutions to things
it's the silo thinking that that
sometimes create the wrong emphasis in a
project and then that normally bites us
in the back later in the in the process
so navigating this complexity is tricky
there's unfortunately I wasn't aware
that the screen was gonna be this small
so I'm fully aware that most people in
the back roles will not be able to read
all of what's on these slides I will
give the slides to Ruth and Ruth will
send them out to you and there's lots of
hyperlinks in in the give it as a PDF
and so all the resources you can
directly follow up on so don't worry
about that bit but what what I'm trying
to say with this slide is that I wrote I
wrote this book called designing
regenerative cultures and in many ways
there's a paradox in this title because
cultures aren't designed cultures emerge
through our relationships and our
interact
with each other but in these complex
systems once you accept that they are
fundamentally unpredictable and
uncontrollable and so the aim is not how
do we manipulate it and enforce a
particular future then you can start
look at what is it that I can do to make
it more likely that the emergent
property the new part of this complex
system that we can't predict that
suddenly pops up will be positive rather
than negative and when you look deeply
into this you find that it is about
building qualitative relationships
paying attention to what kind of
information flows who talks to whom how
deep those relationships are and as you
nourish these somewhat intangible parts
of the system and you so that's why
education is so important because the
information that flows makes a big
difference in the system that will
enable you to create a higher likelihood
that what will emerge unpredictably is a
healthier and a more positive system and
these images again unfortunately you
can't read all of them just reminding
you that we all sit at the beginning of
the slide that there was the word glocal
it wasn't a misspelling I'm actually
talking about global/local at the same
time and whole systems design is about
always being aware of the scale linking
between your little project in your
little neighborhood into the city and
the city region and the nation and how
does it make a difference globally
through implementing for example the
SDGs and so as a practice of a
practitioner wanting to bring about
change this graph up there in the top
right says you've got your project and
then you've got the primary hold the
place that you're in and then you have
the proximate hole which is the slightly
wider region and one thing that is
amazing in terms of making local
projects more powerful is when you ask
yourself the question how does my local
project contribute meaningfully in a
positive way to that proximate greater
Hall it will help you with funding it
will help you with the the meaning for
people in getting engaged in your local
project this this comes from pamela mang
and there's actually a book has this
type of regenerative cultures there's a
whole movement around regenerative
development and the pioneers of that
movement and it's a group called
Regenesis group and they've created a
whole training how to get engaged with
regenerative development so again I'd
encourage you to look into that um in
summary to this slide it's it's always
understanding that since everything is
interconnected
there's always constituent if you think
of your own body there are cells that
make up organs that make up your body is
you sit within a family that sits within
a community within an ecosystem within
the planet and health and wholeness has
a scale
linking quality so if we work for a
better world we can work on any of these
scales and we should always be mindful
of how our actions at any of those
scales impact the other scales again
this is a set of like that that the
subtitle of my book and the working
title while I was writing it was
actually living the questions together
and for me that's why on these cards
that you played with earlier there are
lots of questions questions are enabling
they give people like you you're
actually asking people to engage and to
come together around a certain issue if
you just talk at them they'll listen or
they don't listen but there's there's
something really powerful in questions
and to my mind one of the things that
we've got wrong is that we always want
to jump towards solution
and answers may be a wise culture in the
future would give a catalogue of
questions to the next generation rather
than the answers because if you think of
it most of today's problems were
yesterday's solutions so how could we
assume that our all our most
well-meaning solutions that we're
working on today are not going to turn
into problems for the next generation so
and again an invitation to be mindful of
the power of questions and these
questions won't run through all of them
a distillation of having looked at what
normally goes wrong when we work with
complex systems we do things like we set
the wrong goals or we try to just look
at one isolated parameter rather than
optimizing the system of the whole so
the most classic example is that we've
built a global economy and national
economies that measure everything in GDP
and GDP is actually not an emetic
it's an inadequate measure of progress
and when you fight a war when you have a
national catastrophe GDP goes up and so
we need better indicators of progress
and we need to make sure that when we
work with systems that our like we try
to optimize the system as a whole rather
than just work with isolated parts and
in the interest of time I'm not going to
go through all of them but again I would
really encourage you to look at the PDF
when you when you get it another aspect
that is about that the key things that
that motivate us to actually become
active to step into this small actions
can make a big difference
attitude is to understand that we've
been told an erroneous story about what
life is all about somehow it has crept
in that life is all about scarce
resources and survival of the fittest
and competition and some winners and
some losers this is how we set up our
storytelling and our storytelling is
powerful it creates the world
we we think we live in and we actually
bring forth a world and conversation and
I am originally trained as a biologist
and I can tell you that the way
evolution works since the beginning is
it is a process of diversification and
subsequent reintegration of that
diversity at higher levels of complexity
and this reintegration happens more
often than not through collaboration and
not through competition so while there
is a little bit of competition in the
world we have we've seen the nature
programs where we see the lion kill the
the new it that's that's like ripples on
the surface it's like standing in front
of the ocean and being distracted by the
waves so much that you can't see the
water underneath but really life is all
about a sea of symbiosis and working
together in collaboration and if we
reconnect to that then we can refit in
because we are part of nature it's
another very dangerous bit of
storytelling when whenever you hear your
self or others use language in a way
where you have kind of groups culture
there and nature here remind yourself
and others that culture is an
epiphenomenon of nature we are first and
foremost biological beings and and so a
part of this movement of diversification
and subsequent reintegration of
diversity at higher levels of complexity
and really that's what we're called for
as a species right now with all the
converging crises we're facing if we
don't address them as one humanity and
redesign the human presence on earth
within the lifetime of the generations
alive today
then the earth will continue but
probably we will force the climate
system and all sorts of other issues
around the planet to a point where the
life-support system will not support
higher life-forms like human beings so
we will have greatly impoverished planet
without
we're a young immature species facing a
rite of passage and an opportunity to
grow up as a species and make a
difference and I feel like everyone in
this room being called to a conference
like this already knows this to some
extent and wants to be part of building
that tomorrow's land where there's still
a space for humanity another resource
that I would would like to encourage you
to look at is this book called
regenerative enterprises and it it again
looks at how do we build the subtitle of
my talk how do we build ikan systems of
collaboration and one of the things that
when I read this that really struck me
is designed for your own death if you
have an organization don't assume that
the most important thing is to keep your
organization going if you walk in
ecosystems of collaboration it doesn't
matter if you've served your purpose for
five years ten years and then you merge
with another company or like with
another player in the field or you you
dissolve and all your skills feed other
businesses we very often create these
organizations in good attempt like green
peas or WWF and then they become so
massive that they become to some extent
self-serving first rather than
continuing fully with their mission so
just keep keep this in mind this
flexibility that death is life's
wonderful way to create plenty of life
death is not so boring
both on the personal level or the level
of your company so this is the book
where all of this is kind of put
together and don't worry you don't have
to buy the book it's it's on my medium
block and the block is linked at the end
so you can just read it chapter by
chapter and should you be interested if
you're interested also have a few copies
and again there's a number of questions
around how do we build stronger social
innovation and community participation
that there are from my book and the
images
I put in there just to if you're not
aware of Bali which is a network in
around the Philadelphia area and the
states called the Business Alliance for
local living economies to have a look at
their work it's it's a wonderful model
and anybody anywhere in Europe and
asking themselves how could we translate
what they did in the Philadelphia area
to our region and network local
businesses into this web of local living
of a local living economy and I would
would say that it's it will energize
your work in your region and coming to a
close just a little anecdote by my
colleague and and CEO at guy education
may East once shared with me her daily
practice in the morning and for me it
was an achy moment because be up to that
point I kind of got tired of the word
activist and because it felt too much
like fighting against something there
was always this I'm an activist and I
don't like this and the banks are the
baddies or the government is the baddie
in em and so she told me that when she
gets up in the morning after her morning
meditation she asks herself what is it
that I want to activate with the power
of my attention today what what story
do I want to continue and we all can
make a big big difference every day
simply by asking ourselves that question
it's it's a redefinition of what
activism is about where do we put the
power of our personal attention what
kind of conversations do we have are we
building tomorrow's land in a way that
works for all or are we just Pickering
about why things aren't working today so
I would encourage you to just keep that
in mind and be mindful of how our
stories that the stories we continued
telling this
as we change really make a difference
and he can stay in touch with me it's
all along on the PDF you'll get and
these images really to show that we've
got we're on the bifurcation point in
this complex system that we're part of
we have the opportunity of building a
more abundant world the world that works
for all at the global scale starting
locally but collaborating globally and
again if anybody ever tells you well
that's a great project how do we scale
it up that's the wrong question the
right question is how do we scale it out
because bigger isn't better bigger very
often destroys projects but scaling out
saying ooh Bali that interesting things
in the States
what can I take in terms of the DNA and
the core ideas of what they did and how
can I make it relevant to the bio
cultural uniqueness of place this is in
a nutshell what regenerative working
regenerative lis is all about you work
with people in place you get close to
the story of that place what that played
the essence of that place and you create
elegant solutions that are carefully
adapted to the bio cultural uniqueness
of place and I feel many of you are
already doing this and thank you for
listening to me for half an hour
[Applause]